So at this stage, we have discussed almost every code block that is available to us.
However, there's just one more thing a code block and a coding concept so important to programming
that I needed to wait until you were a pretty competent programmer before I introduced it to you.
And that is functions.
So what is a function and why should we care about it?
Imagine you have a toy making machine, which would be pretty cool.
So you put in some materials, press a button, and out comes a toy car.
And every time you want a new car, you just press the button again and out comes a car.
Although the only problem with this machine is each time it's the same car.
Now imagine you have another machine that is even better, because if you want a red car, you put red
paint and out comes a red car.
Or if you want a blue car, you put in blue paint and out comes a blue car.
You get the idea.
Well, both of these machines are examples of functions, except one of the functions allows inputs
which can change the output.
Now, in the world of coding, functions are like that magical button.
You write a piece of code once, and then you can use it over and over again just by calling the functions
name.
Now some functions can accept inputs like a number or string, and depending on what the input is,
determines what output the function will give you.
Just like our car making machine that gives different color cars, but as well some functions will always
return the same output.
So how do functions work?
Well first we write a function.
It's like building our toy making machine, setting it up to make a particular toy.
Next, any time we need that specific task done, we call the function just like pressing the button
on the machine.
The function then executes the task and gives us the result, just like the machine popping out a toy
car.
So why are functions important in programming?
I'm sure you could probably already guess why.
Firstly, saving time without functions, we would have to write the same code again and again and again
for the same similar tasks.
Functions save us time.
We write once and we use many, many times.
Next.
Organizing code functions help us keep our code clean and organized.
Each function has its job, and it makes it easier to track down and fix any issues.
Thirdly, less mistakes.
Having one piece of code means there's only one place to check and fix if something goes wrong.
No more searching through blocks and blocks of code.
And lastly, sharing code functions can also be shared between different parts of our program or even
between different programs.
And as you know, reusable code is so important.
So imagine this.
You're creating an exciting game where a brave knight goes on a quest.
During this quest, the knight encounters treasure chests.
Now, each time the knight touches a chest, it opens up and tadaa.
The coins inside it all jump out.
Now here's the catch.
Our game has not one, not two, but many treasure chests scattered in different levels.
We want every chest to do the same magical opening act.
So how can we make this happen without writing the same code for every single chest?
Here comes the function.
We can write a function named Open Chest that contains the code to make the chest open and coins pop
out.
Now, every time the knight touches a chest, we simply call the open chest function.
It's like telling the game, hey, do the chest opening thing now and voila!
The chest opens and coins come out and ta da!
And no matter where the chest is in the game, it works.
And to give you a real world scratch example of functions in DOS, there is a popular project in scratch
called Smooth Movement Engine, and I encourage you to check it out for yourself.
But clicking play on this project.
Notice how all these sprites move in a very fluid motion.
And if we click next.
And next again you can see all the projects that utilize smooth movement.
Anyway, if we click this see inside button, you will see that there is this code block called Custom
Block.
And if we zoom out you will see all the different functions.
And yes, they're quite complex.
So don't worry about trying to understand how it works.
The important thing here is what the functions do.
So if we move over to the My Blocks tab you'll see all these different blocks.
But basically these blocks are all used to call the functions.
So let's say we had a sprite and we wanted it to move up.
So let's first delete all these sprites so you can see this in action and also show the sprite.
Now we want to ask where sprite to move forward 100 steps.
Now, instead of using the movement code block, we can call this function here.
So as you can see this block gives a lot of options.
So let's say we wanted to move 100 steps in two seconds with an easing type of one.
Clicking play.
As you can see, our sprite moves smoothly down our screen.
So now let's say we wanted to turn and move forward again so we could grab this smooth turn block.
So let's say we want to smooth turn 45 degrees in one second with a easing type of three.
Then we can just duplicate this other smooth movement and stick it at the end.
Now if we hit play, notice how our sprite moves slowly and smoothly forward.
Then takes a smooth turn and finally moves forward again.
And all I took was three blocks of code.
But if we were trying to manually create the smooth movement for each movement, it would take ages
and our code would be so confusing to understand what was actually going on.
So in summary, functions are one of the programmer's best tools to write efficient, organized, and
clean code.
In coding, a function is like a handy helper that does a specific job whenever we ask it, and it's
so reliable, we know it works because it's been tested and reused.
And so by mastering functions, you're well on your way to becoming a skilled coder who can make complex
and interactive programs.